Here we go. All right, and I'm letting
everybody in from the waiting room of
the lobby. So, good afternoon,
everybody. Just as a reminder,
um
this is the dosage administration
um committee meeting.
I'm sorry, a dosage administration and
clinical practice committee meeting um
with Ian Dunn as the chair. I'm Dr.
Dominick Rodriguez, and I'm the director
for the New Mexico Department of Health
Medical Cannabis and Psilocybin Center.
And so, um
with that, I will turn it on over to
Ian.
Um oh, with just the reminder that we
are recording the meeting, so please
remember to use appropriate language as
we do post these up on our website. We
want to make sure they are available for
all individuals. So, and with that, it
is your meeting, Ian.
>> Hello. Good afternoon, everyone. My name
is Ian Dunn. I am the chair of the
Dosage Administration and Clinical
Practice Committee. I call this meeting
to order.
Um
what we are going to be going over today
is a follow-up on the integration
sessions. It should have been sent out
last week to all attendees of that
meeting and the meeting before
um
for what we can start to circle around.
So, we had some ideas come up in the
last meeting
um
around circle of care methods, other
integration approaches, and just
generally how to make integration a more
reasonable thing. Um Dominick, if you
could pull up the integration sessions
while anyone that would like to
participate, if you would like to
introduce yourself, you may.
And again, if If would like to introduce
yourself at this time, you may raise
your hand um or put it in the chat as
well.
>> Okay, and Ian, I am not seeing any hands
raised. Um we do have introduction in
the
chat. Looks like it's coming up. Sky
Rivers with Santa Fe Reporter. Good
afternoon, everyone. Happy to be here.
>> Perfect. Well, we will then we will just
go ahead and dive into the document. Um
and if you still would like to introduce
yourself in chat, you may. Uh we will go
ahead and address those as they come in.
Um but for integration, integration is
the process of incorporating those
insights, emotions, and experiences
arising from medical psilocybin
treatment into a patient's daily life,
their long-term health goals, um and
overall well-being.
The purpose of integration is to support
the translation of acute psychedelic
experiences into meaningful and
sustained psychological, behavioral, um
and functional change while promoting
um patient safety and continuity of
care.
Integration is most effective when
supported by an individualized circle of
care consisting of the patient, their
provider, um and when authorized by the
patient, other members of the patient's
support network. The circle of care can
include family members, trusted friends,
behavioral health providers, primary
care clinicians, peer support
specialists, recovery support, spiritual
care providers, and other individuals
identified by the patient.
And whenever appropriate and with the
patient's written consent, practitioners
are encouraged to coordinate
communication um with their members of
the circle of care. So again, that can
be their behavioral health providers,
their primary care clinicians,
um recovery supports, et cetera.
So,
um this helps to reinforce healthy
behavioral changes, identify emerging
concerns early, and reduce the
fragmentation of care. So, participation
by members of the circle of care should
always respect the patient's autonomy,
their confidentiality, and applicable
privacy laws.
So, this is a the general purpose and
scope discussing what integration is. At
this time, do we have any questions,
comments, or concerns? I did see Don
Moser is here from Las Vegas, New
Mexico.
Alrighty.
And seeing no hands, um, we will go
ahead and move on to the general
principles. Uh, integration planning
should begin during the preparation
phase of treatment. Whenever
practicable, integration appointments
should be scheduled before the
administration session, so patients are
not expected to coordinate follow-up
care,
um, immediately after treatment.
Individualized care integration should
be tailored to the patient's clinical
presentation, their treatment goals,
their cultural background, and response
to the administration session. Providers
should adjust the timing, frequency, and
intensity of integration services when
clinically indicated, including
following a particularly challenging or
highly meaningful experience.
Um, and we also should have
patient-centered approaches. Um,
integration should be collaborative. It
shouldn't be direct It shouldn't be
directive. Um, they should be supporting
the patients in exploring the meaning of
their experience without imposing
personal beliefs, spiritual frameworks,
um, and philosophical
philosophical interpretations, or
specific conclusions.
Um, that has been found pretty
substantially throughout research, um,
that we should not be directive in
providing that care.
So, any, uh, questions, comments,
concerns on that section?
Cool.
And then moving on to the circle of care
methods, um, this comes from the
psychedelic mental health alliance. do
want to give them their credit. Um
evidence-informed integration may
include one or more of the following
methods when clinically appropriate and
within the practitioner's scope of
practice. So, it can be individual
sessions, group integration sessions,
family or support person education,
care coordination, um referral to
community-based peer support, values
clarification and behavioral activation,
reflective practices such as journaling,
expressive arts or structured structured
narrative exercises, mindfulness and
grounding exercises, um somatic
awareness and regulation techniques, the
goal setting using measurable and
achievable behavioral objectives, and
the scheduled follow-up contacts between
formal integration sessions when
clinically indicated.
Um so, these are their general circle of
care what can be used in integration um
to help develop those
the incorporation into their daily lives
of what they um
developed or learned from their
psychedelic experience.
At this time, any questions, comments,
or concerns?
All righty. So, then we will go ahead
and move forward to integrative care
planning.
So, during preparation, practitioners
should collaborate with patients to
identify members of their circle of care
um if they already exist or whether we
need to work on finding them, discuss
anticipated integration needs, and
develop a preliminary plan for their
follow-up support. So, integration may
include one or more evidence-informed
approaches appropriate to the patient's
treatment plan and practitioner scope of
practice.
When a patient has an established
therapist, counselor, psychiatrist, or
other behavioral health provider, the
medical psilocybin provider is
encouraged, with the patient's written
consent, to coordinate care and
facilitate continuity of treatment. This
again goes alongside with um trying to
reduce costs with in Medicaid at
Um
because if they are already working with
a behavioral health specialist,
um and they are able to go back to them
for some of the development,
um
that could help reduce costs on them if
they already had worked on finding uh
someone approved by their health
insurance.
Any questions, comments, concerns?
>> [clears throat]
>> All righty, then let's go ahead and talk
about the integration timeline.
So, immediately post-session before
discharge, we want to screen for
psychological distress, um emergent
suicidal ideation, manic symptoms,
severe anxiety, then provide the patient
with clear written protocols after our
crisis contacts, local emergency
services,
um and designated support contacts.
Practitioners should advise patients to
refrain from making major life-altering
decisions, um example, occupational,
financial, relational,
for at least 2 to 4 weeks post-session
to allow space for integration.
So, that initial check-in is almost
administrative. It's not really a true
integration session, um but it's just
assessing that physical recovery, their
psychological stability, making sure
they're not still experiencing sleep
disruption 72 hours after, that their
appetite has returned, that their mood
has stabilized, and that they have
general functioning. Not meant to be a
full um top-to-bottom in-person
assessment, but just a general check-in
to say, "Hey,
um make sure they're still okay." And
make sure that there are still plans to
um
further integrate.
Then the ongoing integration that
happens 72 hours after uh integration.
It is about translating the insights
into the achievable behavioral goals,
um
processing unresolved emotions or
difficult experiences, identifying
changes that support the patient's
treatment objectives,
um developing coping strategies and
grounding techniques, strengthening
healthy relationships and community
supports, and determining whether
additional behavioral health services or
referrals are clinically appropriate.
So, the number and frequency of
integration sessions should be
determined by clinical judgment and
individual patient needs.
And then, um in
any questions, comments, concerns about
the timeline section?
Cool. Then, we can go ahead and move on
to documentation.
Again, these are just best practices and
guidelines,
um but practitioners should document all
integration sessions in the medical
record within 48 hours of service
delivery. Documentation should include
the date, duration, and setting, um
the summary of the dosing experience and
key emerging themes, assessment of
mental health status, mood, sleep, and
functional status, objective measures,
um and this would be, of course,
relative to the specific condition being
treated. So, um for instance, a PHQ-9
for depression. Doesn't have to be that
one for depression. I know that there
are multiple scales, um
but just an example of whatever
objective measures that they're going to
use.
Um and any reported adverse events or
clinical concerns along with
corresponding intervention plans,
um updates to the overarching treatment
plan, and care coordination efforts.
So, now as a whole, um
any questions, comments, concerns on the
integration guidance?
Don Moser.
Don, I've enabled your microphone.
>> Okay.
>> [clears throat]
>> I may have missed it, but um who is
handling the the post
uh session integration? Is it Is it the
um
the patient's
personal practitioner or is it
the practitioner involved with the
um administration?
>> So, there are a number of different ways
that people can integrate into
the program. Um
I believe under the current status quo
one would have to be from the
psychedelic therapist or the
practitioner,
but Dominic, you can correct me if I am
wrong.
>> No, you are correct, Ian. I mean, it
should should be with the same
practitioner or therapist that the
patient is going through for both their
preparatory and during administration.
And then, of course, the facilitator
should also be involved with regard to
that. But it is ultimately up to the
patient, and if the patient would like
to do it through their own Like if they
have a different therapist and they want
to work through some of that, then that
is the choice of the patient.
>> [clears throat]
>> Okay. Well, thank you very much.
>> Any other questions, comments, concerns?
And thank you, Don Don.
Already. Well, I have reached out to uh
Brenda, Larry Lehman, and
Kate Hawk. I still haven't heard back
from Kate Hawk yet. Um
so
I haven't heard any objections yet, but
does anyone have any reason that they
would not support this
integration session guidance as stands?
Already, then why don't we go ahead and
take a vote? All of those in favor of
adopting this integration session
guidance, please raise your hand at this
time.
All right, I see two up.
Please, or three up, please lower your
hands at this time.
And then, if you are opposed, please
raise your hand.
All right, and I am seeing none. So, we
will go ahead and adopt the integration
session guidance. What I would like to
work on going forward is general
guidance regarding the specific
qualifying conditions and their dosage
regimes.
Um
and how we can not say, per se, limit
what a patient can receive, but what the
general best practices are.
Um
like I know for PTSD, there's been some
studies with a flat 25 mg and some
studies with an ascending 15 to 25. So,
just preparation for discussions around
the specific qualifying conditions. Um
and what their dosage regime should be.
And
I think that would make for good
conversation. Does anyone else have
something they would like to say? I was
not expecting no questions.
Alrighty. Well, if there are no further
questions, then we can begin um
working individually on our dosage
guidelines for
the
different qualifying conditions.
Um
and work on
getting those prepped and ready.
When would you guys like to meet up
again?
Let's see.
Uh Sky?
>> Oh, okay, [clears throat] good. Good
Good afternoon, Ann. Um I have a
question about the dosage that you just
spoke about. Say one qualifying
condition is 25 mg. And then you said
another one could be like 15 to 25. So,
my question would be if someone starts
with 15 mg
and they need more. I always thought
that if you add something an hour later,
it's not working, you add more.
Doesn't it last longer or take away or
isn't there a
not a time frame. I'm not sure what I'm
looking for. I'm not a pharmacist, but
a certain amount of time where
well, we need more and we need more and
then at one point it just kind of drags
on cuz you add it an hour later to the
process. Do you know what I'm talking
about? Can you explain that to me?
>> Yeah, so every time that you add a new
amount of a medication
uh well, hold on. Let me go back a
little bit. Um each medication has a
peak and trough of how high the volume
of it that's in your blood is.
So, when a medication is at its most
strong you're at its peak and then when
it you're wears off you're at its
trough. So, every time you add new
medication, you're re-trying to draw
that peak and trough graph. And so, it
pushes it out and basically restarts the
clock each time.
So,
medications have what's known as a
half-life.
Um
basically the amount of time for half of
the drug that is consumed to be out of
your body.
Each time
it requires five half-lives to clear it
entirely. Each time that a you add new
medication, you're resetting that five
half-life
timer.
>> Okay, so it doesn't it doesn't last
longer. It's just adding to the effect.
That's what happens.
>> So, well, you're doing two things,
right? When you add more of a dose of
something, right? You're going to make
it stronger A and then
B, you're going to restart the amount of
time it takes to clear from your body.
>> Right. Okay.
>> So,
I would always say like we should at
least monitor for 8 hours past the last
administration session.
>> Mhm.
>> Um the last time the mushroom touched
their tongue. Um
but
it is a very variable thing. When you
add more though, you're restarting that
8-hour timer.
I hope that makes sense.
>> Yeah, I I'm following you. So, it gets a
bit stronger as you add, it can get
stronger even though it's
gone down in strength. When you add more
than it doubles the strength?
Am I making sense? Then it gets more
powerful?
>> Well, it it's relative to the amount
that you So, if you take 10 mg and then
an hour later you take another 10 mg,
>> Right.
>> you're still going to get a point where
you'll have the effect of roughly 20 mg.
>> Okay.
>> But
it's not going to be like
as
you delayed the onset a little bit. So,
it's going to be a slower come up
instead of being a very quick um
come up.
>> Is one way better than the other? Safer
than the other? Depending on the
>> So,
>> cations?
>> Um
in the research, the ascending is
actually not too like a 15 mg and then a
25 mg in the same day. They're saying to
take um a 15 mg and then 2 weeks 3 weeks
later take their 25 mg. That one's
regarded as the more safe one cuz you
get to see an entry level and sure that
there's no dissociation,
depersonalization, anything like that.
And then you go to the full-size dose.
Um but there's also a good substantial
or a good amount of evidence that
psilocybin is pretty safe in general.
And therefore, it may not be worth the
additional caution to start off.
>> Okay.
>> I'm an always an abundance of caution
person, but there are different thoughts
out there currently.
>> Thank you.
>> All right, any other questions,
comments, concerns?
All right, then I will ask Dominic when
the department is free for us to meet
next.
>> Uh so, what what frequency would you
like?
Is going to be the first question.
>> Well, I know the board is going to have
to address both training and education
and equity first. So, there's no real
need to like rush.
Um
we could do
>> Well, I was just going to suggest we do
have Wednesday the 16th of September,
same time, is open.
>> That works for me. That is okay with
everyone in the chat or in the meeting.
>> I'm not hearing any objections, so
Okay. So, we will get it scheduled for
Wednesday the 16th starting at 1:00.
>> Perfect. Already.
Well, thank you everyone for being here.
I appreciate your time today. This was a
very fast meeting, but I hope we have a
little bit more discussion at our next
one.
Um
thank you everyone for being here. I
really appreciate it and have a great
rest of your Wednesday.
>> And on behalf of the department, thank
every Thank you everyone. Hope you have
a great day.